Hugo Gernsback Papers
Hugo Gernsback Papers
1890-1995
Gernsback, Hugo, 1884-1967
30 linear ft.
Correspondence, memorabilia, writings, and publications of the Luxembourg-American author, editor, publisher, and entrepreneur in the fields of amateur radio, electronics, and science fiction.
148999
Biographical History
Hugo Gernsback (1884-1967) was a Luxembourg-American author, editor, publisher, and entrepreneur in the fields of amateur radio, electronics, and science fiction. For his contributions to the latter, including creating the first magazine dedicated to the genre ( Amazing Stories, 1926), he has often been called "the father of science fiction." The Hugo Awards, presented at the annual World Science Fiction Convention, are named for him.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Hugo Gernsback Papers consists of correspondence, Gernsback publications, memorabilia, subject files, and writings.
The relatively small amount of Correspondence is primarily from the mid-1950s, and is almost entirely incoming. Most relates to various endeavors of Gernsback's, such as his efforts to interest commercial fisheries in his patented hydraulic device and a letter to Latin American distributors regarding a Spanish-language edition of Radio-Electronics. Other correspondents include colleagues and collaborators such as Marc Lanval, David Sarnoff, and Austin Lescarboura, and fellow science fiction enthusiasts such as Sam Moskowitz.
Material relating to Gernsback publications includes a small amount of business records (advertisements, copyright and trademark registrations, form letters, and so on) and a considerable amount of printed material published by Gernsback under one or another of his company names. Most are "how-to" manuals for the amateur radio enthusiast; some are standalone titles ( 101 short wave hookups, How to build and operate short wave receivers, Radio trouble finder) while others were published as part of a named series (The Experimenter's Library, Radio Tinker's Library, etc.). There are also catalogs from Gernsback's Electro Importing Company and Radio Trading Co., milestone anniversary issues of Radio-Craft and Radio-Electronics, and a reprint of radio, telephone, and telegraphic equipment from the Montgomery Ward catalog. The miscellaneous material at the end of this series contains two pieces of artwork from the 1940s by science fiction illustrator Alex Schomburg, but otherwise mostly dates from the 1980s and 1990s and thus has little connection with Gernsback.
Memorabilia includes awards, clippings, photographs, and assorted other items, which together illustrate Gernsback's impact on amateur radio and on science fiction. Among the earliest items is a "Budding Electrician" certificate from the Carmelite Convent in Luxembourg, bestowed for installing "our electrical bell system, gratis" -- it is dated 1890, meaning that Gernsback would have been about six years old at the time. At the end of this series are a few artifacts, mostly unidentifiable but likely related to short wave radio construction.
The vast majority of material in the Subject files consists of photographs, either original or reproductions, of a wide range of home, commercial, and industrial electronics and technology. Many of the photographs have detailed typed captions. Other formats include negatives, color transparencies, drawings, sketches, and occasionally product literature, correspondence, and clippings. Subjects range from amplifiers, microphones, and tuners to spaceships, moon radio, and satellites. A few folders pertain to individuals (Nikola Tesla, Lee De Forest) while "Biographies" and "Portraits" contain brief descriptions and photographs, respectively, of important individuals in the field. These files, which have been preserved as originally arranged, undoubtedly served as reference/source material for Gernsback's magazines during his life, and continued to be used and added to after his death.
Writings contains articles, books, letters to the editor, manuals, speeches, stories, and miscellaneous items by Gernsback. Included here are his editorials for Amazing Stories, Electrical Experimenter, Everyday Science and Mechanics, Radio News, Radio & Television, Radio-Craft, Radio-Electronics, Science fiction Plus, Science and Invention, Science Wonder Stories, Short Wave Craft, Television News, and Wonder Stories. Many of his pieces predict, propose, or describe technology that was novel at the time but is common today, such as telemedicine ("Call the teledoctor"), desalination ("Miracle from the Sea"), text-to-speech ("A writing machine that responds to the voice"), and drones ("The radio-controlled television plane"). There are several editions of his novel Ralph 124C 41+, including a German edition, as well as his story "Scientific adventures of Baron Munchausen" as published in Amazing Stories. Also included are fifteen years of Forecast, Gernsback's annual holiday booklet in which he laid out his science and technology predictions for the coming year, and a number of his humorous/parody Christmas magazines.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is alphabetical by correspondent. Gernsback publications are subdivided into business records (alphabetical by format or topic) and printed material (alphabetical by title). Memorabilia is alphabetical by title or topic. Subject files remain in original order and with original titles. Writings are subdivided by type (articles, books, etc.) and within each type are alphabetical by title. The few writings by others, at the end of the series, are alphabetical by author's name.
Related Material
has extensive holdings related to science fiction and pulp-era publishing in both its manuscript and published holdings. Related corporate collections include
Ace Books
,
Galaxy Publishing Company
,
Mercury Press
, and
Street and Smith
. Individual collections include
Forrest Ackerman
,
Anne McCaffrey
,
Piers Anthony
,
Theodore Cogswell
,
Murray Leinster
,
Neil R. Jones
,
Keith Laumer
,
Andre Norton
, and
Kate Wilhelm
. Cataloged material includes magazines such as If and Astounding, as well as fanzines and conference programs. Please refer to to locate cataloged items, and to for a full list of related manuscript collections.
Many of Gernsback's publications are available in digital format on the World Radio History website.
Separated Material
The collection originally contained extensive runs of periodicals for which Gernsback was the editor, publisher, or both. These have been cataloged. Please refer to to locate these items.
Titles include: Air wonder stories, Amazing detectives, Amazing stories, Aviation mechanics, Electrical experimenter, Everyday mechanics, Everyday science and mechanics, The experimenter, Facts of life, Flight, Foto-craft, French humor, Gadgets, High sea adventures, Know yourself, Life guide, Light, Luz, Milady, Modern electrics, Moneymaking, Motor camper & tourist, New ideas for everybody, Pirate stories, Popular medicine, Practical electrics, Radio amateur news, Radio & television, Radio-craft, Radio-electronics, Radio electronics weekly business letter, Radio listeners guide and call book, Radio news, Radio program weekly, Radio review, Science and invention, Science fiction, Science wonder stories, Scientific detective monthly, Sexologia, Sexology, Short wave and television, Short wave craft, Superworld comics, Technocracy review, Television, Television news, Woman's Digest, Wonder stories, Your body, and: Your dreams.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Literature -- American Fiction; Publishing, printing and book arts; Popular culture; Radio, television, film; Science fiction; Ackerman, Forrest J.; De Forest, Lee, 1873-1961.; Ernsting, Walter, 1920-2005.; Fitch, Clyde, 1865-1909.; Gernsback, Hugo, 1884-1967.; Gernsback, Hugo, 1884-1967. -- Baron Münchausen's Scientific Adventures.; Gernsback, Hugo, 1884-1967. -- Ralph 124C 41+; Gernsback, Sidney, 1876-; Kazantsev, Aleksandr, 1906-2002.; Lanval, Marc, 1898-; Lescarboura, Austin C. (Austin Celestin), 1891-; Menzel, Donald H. (Donald Howard), 1901-1976.; Mims, Forrest M.; Moskowitz, Sam.; Pomeroy, Wardell B. (Wardell Baxter), 1913-2001.; Sarnoff, David, 1891-1971.; Schomburg, Alex.; Secor, H. W. (Harry Winfield), 1887-; Tesla, Nikola, 1856-1943.; Electro Importing Company.; Engineering Society of Detroit.; MIT Science Fiction Society.; New York University.; Radio Club of America.; Radio Corporation of America.; Radio Trading Co.; Society of Wireless Pioneers.; Air wonder stories.; Amazing stories.; Electrical experimenter.; Everyday science and mechanics.; Forecast.; Know yourself.; Modern electrics.; Popular electronics.; Radio amateur news.; Radio & television.; Radio news.; Radio-craft.; Radio-electronics.; Science and invention.; Science fiction plus.; Science wonder stories.; Sexology.; Short wave and television.; Short wave craft.; Technocracy review.; Television news.; Utopia Sonderband.; Wonder stories.; The experimenter's library.; The radio tinker's library.; Radio-craft library.; Automobiles -- Radio equipment.; Authors, American.; Editors -- United States.; Electronic apparatus and appliances -- Photographs.; Electronics -- Amateurs' manuals.; Electronics -- Periodicals.; Luxembourg Americans.; Military art and science.; Periodical editors.; Periodicals -- Publishing.; Popular literature -- United States.; Publishers and publishing -- United States.; Radio -- Amateurs' manuals.; Radio -- History.; Radio -- Periodicals.; Radio broadcasting -- Social aspects.; Radio broadcasting -- History.; Radio control.; Science fiction -- Illustration.; Science fiction -- Periodicals.; Science publishing.; Sexuality -- Periodicals.; Shortwave radio -- Periodicals.; Space flight.; Technical writing.; Technological innovations.; Technology -- Periodicals.; Television -- History.; Television -- Periodicals.; Luxembourg.; United States -- Popular culture.; Articles.; Biographical sketches.; Clippings (information artifacts); Color transparencies.; Correspondence.; Cylinders (sound recordings); Drafts (documents); Editorials.; Lantern slides.; Manuscripts for publication.; Negatives (photographs); Negative prints.; Patents.; Periodicals.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Speeches (documents); Authors.; Editors.; Inventors.; Publishers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Hugo Gernsback, Harvey Gernsback, Gernsback estate, and Adria Coren, 1965-2005.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Ackerman, Forrest J, 1949-1950; 1957 (Box 1)
  - Adalia Ltd., 1953 (Box 1)
  - Aisberg, E., 1964 (Box 1)
  - Blair, William R., 1957 (Box 1)
  - Boucheron, Pierre, 1945 (Box 1)
  - Commissioner of Patents, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Cummings, Edward H., 1913; 1966; includes tribute to Gernsback (Box 1)
  - De Forest, Lee, 1942-1961 (Box 1)
  - Dunn, Gordon E., 1954 (Box 1)
  - Editions Satellite, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - Frederick Fell, Inc., 1950 (Box 1)
  - Hebert, Arthur A., 1937 (Box 1)
  - Henry Ford Museum, undated (Box 1)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Hydraulic fisheries queries, 1957; letters to various pipe manufacturers about a patented idea for using hydraulics to suck up fish (Box 1)
  - IBM "Think" magazine, 1962; rejection letter (Box 1)
  - Iceland Defense Force, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Independent News Co. Inc., 1979 (Box 1)
  - Institut für Küsten- und Binnenfischerei [Institute for Inshore and Inland Fisheries], 1958-1965 (Box 1)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B., 1957 (Box 1)
  - Kennedy, John F., 1957 (Box 1)
  - Koninklijke Machinenfabrik, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Lanval, Marc, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Latin American distributors, undated; letter regarding possible Spanish edition of Radio-Electronics (Box 1)
  - Lescarboura, Austin, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Luxembourg, Duchy of, 1954; 1959 (Box 1)
  - Marx, Edmond, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Menzel, Donald H., 1953-1958; 1970 (Box 1)
  - McMorrow, Berman, & Davidson, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - Moskowitz, Sam, 1964; includes material related to "First Fandom" award given to Gernsback (Box 1)
  - Musick, Dan, 1964 (Box 1)
  - New magazine contest, 1961; letter to unidentified readers, regarding contest to name a new Gernsback magazine that would focus on the latest technological developments (Box 1)
  - New York University (NYU), 1950; 1954,; 1958; mostly related to establishment of Gernsback Scholarship; includes photographs of first four recipients (Box 1)
  - Philco Corp., 1955 (Box 1)
  - "Radio Amateur News" announcement, 1919; letter to unidentified readers, announcing new magazine (Box 1)
  - Rommel, Allwine, & Rommel, 1961; 1963; patent/trademark attorneys (Box 1)
  - Sarnoff, David, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Scott Meredith, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Steckler, Larry, 1962 (Box 1)
  - U.S. Naval Communication Station, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Watson-Watt, Robert, 1963; 1973 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Gernsback publications
  - Business records
    - Advertising broadsides, 1907; undated (Oversize 1)
      See also Memorabilia: Photographs: Electro Importing Co. below.
      Electro Importing Company, 2 items: "Our new fall line" broadside with pictures of items, with New York and Brussels addresses; "A few views of our organization" broadside with photos of stockrooms, Gernsback, his offices, etc.
      Radio Trading Co., 1 item: "Radios for 1935 season" broadside with images and descriptions of items
    - Business certificates, 1940; 1987 (Box 2)
    - Copyright registrations, 1926-1965; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Credit memos from manufacturers, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - Form letters (Box 2)
    - Notarized receipts for stories, 1929; proofs of 3 stories, signed and notarized as received (Box 2)
    - "Paleozoic Primitive Art", 1943; includes Radio-Craft covers with captions, humorous comments on sales resistance; possibly a marketing presentation (Oversize 2)
    - Science Fiction Plus, 1952-1953; payment records, printing contracts, tables of contents, stamps to advertise magazine, etc. (Box 2)
    - Tape duplicating (Box 2)
    - Trademark registrations, 1919-1910; 1913-1914,; 1929,; 1935-1937,; 1952-1953,; 1955,; 1963 (Box 2)
  - Printed material
    - 10 most popular short wave receivers: How to make and work them, 1933 (Box 2)
    - 101 short wave hookups, [1932?] (Box 2)
    - 101 short wave hookups, 1936 (Box 2)
    - 150 radio hookups, 1926; "prepared by the staff of Radio News" (Box 2)
    - ABC of television, 1937 (Box 2)
    - Amplifier handbook and public address guide / Moe Asch, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
    - "The Boy's Electric Toys", 1917; full-page ad for kit; instruction book with activities (Box 2)
    - Construction of induction coils and transformers / H. Winfield Secor, 1910; banner across top of front cover says "The Electric Library No. 3" (Box 2)
    - The electrical experimenter, reproductions of miscellaneous pages (Box 2)
    - Electro Importing Co. catalogs, bound [Volume 1], 1905-1912 (Box 8)
      [unnumbered catalog]
      No. 3, 1906
      No. 4, [1907?]
      No. 5, First Edition, 1908
      No. 6, First Edition, 1909
      No. 7, First Edition, 1910
      No. 7, Second Edition, 1910
      No. 8, First Edition, 1910
      No. 9, Second Edition, 1911
      No. 10 [First Edition, 1911]
      No. 10 Second Edition, 1912
      No. 10S First Edition, 1911 [Spanish edition]
    - Electro Importing Co. catalogs, bound [Volume 2], 1909-1912 (Box 8)
      No. 4, Third Edition, 1910
      No. 10, Third Second Edition, 1911
    - Electro Importing Co. catalogs, bound [Volume 3], 1908-1912 (Box 8)
      No. 4, Third Edition, 1908
      No. 10, Third Edition, 1911
      No. 10, Second Edition, 1912
    - Electro Importing Co. catalogs, bound [Volume 4], 1908-1912 (Box 8)
      [unidentified catalog, cover missing]
      No. 6, Second Edition, 1909
    - Electro Importing Co. Catalog No. 10S, First Edition, 1911; Spanish edition (Box 2)
    - Electro Importing Co. Catalog [No. 11?], 1913 (Box 2)
    - Electro Importing Co. Catalog No. 12, First Edition, 1914 (Box 2)
    - Electro Importing Co. Catalog No. 14A, "Electric Holiday Suggestions", [1914 or 1915] (Box 2)
    - Electro Importing Co. Catalog No. 15, First Edition, 1915 (Box 3)
    - Electro Importing Co. Catalog No. 16, First Edition, 1916 (Box 3)
    - Electro Importing Co. Catalog No. 18, First Edition, 1917; cover has additional title "Wireless & Electrical Cyclopedia" (Box 3)
    - Electro Importing Co. Catalog No. 18, Second Edition, 1917; cover has additional title "Wireless & Electrical Cyclopedia" (Box 3)
    - Electro Importing Co. Catalog No. 19, First Edition, 1918; cover has additional title "Wireless & Electrical Cyclopedia" (Box 3)
    - Electro Importing Co. Catalog No. 19, Second Edition, 1918; cover has additional title "Wireless & Electrical Cyclopedia" (Box 3)
    - Electro Importing Co. Catalog No. 21, Second Edition, 1919; cover has additional title "Wireless & Electrical Cyclopedia" (Box 3)
    - Electro Importing Co. Catalog No. 22, First Edition, 1920; cover has additional title "Wireless & Electrical Cyclopedia" (Box 3)
    - Electro Importing Co. Catalog No. 23, Second Edition, 1920; cover has additional title "Wireless & Electrical Cyclopedia" (Box 3)
    - Electro Importing Co. Catalog, unidentified, 1917; heavily marked up and with laid-in notes (Box 3)
    - Electro Importing Co. mailings, miscellaneous, form letters, envelopes, etc. (Box 3)
    - The Experimenter's Library, 1916; 1920; no. 1-3; 3 volumes (Box 3)
      No. 1 - How to make wireless sending apparatus
      No. 2 - How to make wireless receiving apparatus
      No. 3 - Design and construction of audion amplifying transformers, Edward T. Jones
    - The Experimenter's Library, 1922-1924; no. 1-3 (Box 3)
      No. 1 - Tips for the radio amateur constructor, E. Vail Church
      No. 2 - How to make radio-phone receiving sets, R. LaCault
      No. 2 - How to practical radio receiving sets, W.G. Many
      No. 3 - Radio questions answered, A.P. Peck (2 copies)
    - The Experimenter's Library, 1922-1924; no. 4-14 (Box 4)
      No. 4 - Radio frequency amplifiers and how to make them, John M. Avery
      No. 5 - Loud talkers and how to build them, H. Winfield Secor
      No. 6 - How to tune your radio set, Maurice L. Muhleman
      No. 7 - 100 radio hookups, Maurice L. Muhleman
      No. 8 - All about radio parts, Thomas W. Benson
      No. 9 - History and operation of the vacuum tube: The Aladdin's lamp pf radio, J.H. Morecroft
      No. 10 - The neutrodyne: All about it, Maurice L. Muhleman
      No. 11 - How radio is received, R.S. Ould
      No. 12 - How to locate troubles in your radio set, Thomas W. Benson
      No. 13 - Reflex radio receivers, P.E. Edelman
      No. 14 - The super-heterodyne: Theory and construction, F.F. Webb
    - "Frozen" electricity: The electret, 1949 (Box 4)
    - How to become an amateur radio operator, and secure a U.S. government license, by Lt. Myron F. Eddy, 1932 (Box 4)
    - How to build modern loudspeakers, Clyde J. Fitch, 1928 (Box 4)
    - How to build and operate short wave receivers, 1937 (Box 4)
    - How to electrify your radio set, Victor Osgood, 1927 (Box 4)
    - How to get best short wave reception, M. Harvey Gernsback, 1935 (Box 4)
    - Montgomery Ward radio, telephone, and telegraphic equipment, reprinted (presumably from their catalog), with "Compliments of Radio-Electronics Magazine" on the front cover (Box 4)
    - NEW, vol. A no. 1, Sep 1945 (Box 4)
    - Official short wave listener, 1935-1936; vol. 1 no. 5 and vol. 2 no. 4 (Box 4)
    - Radio amateur course, G.W. Shuart, 1937; 2 copies (Box 4)
    - Radio news, reproductions of miscellaneous pages from magazine (Box 4)
    - Radio reference annual, 1938 (Box 4)
    - The Radio Tinker's Library, 1924; 4 volumes (Box 4)
      No. 1 - A guide for the radio builder, F.F. Webb
      No. 2 - The how and why of radio parts, Joseph H. Kraus
      No. 4 - How to build the famous one knob set, W.G. Many
      No. 5 - How to make a neutrodyne receiver, F.F. Webb
    - The Radio Tinker's Library, 1924; 2 volumes (Box 5)
      No. 8 - How to make a resistance coupled amplifier, F.F. Webb
      The radio tinker's log book and broadcast guide, including radio broadcast map of the U.S.
    - Radio Trading Co. catalogs, 1932-1936; no. 24, 25, 26, 27, 27SW, 28, 29, 31; 5 folders (Box 5)
    - The radio trouble finder, 1926; "compiled by the staff of Radio News" (Box 5)
    - Radio-craft, Feb 1931 (Box 5)
    - Radio-craft Jubilee Souvenir Issue, 1938; 1987; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Radio-Craft Library, 1931-1941; no. 1-4, 6-9, 11-14, 16, 18-20, 23-25; no. 1 is captioned "Radio Library"; 18 volumes in 5 folders (Box 5)
      No. 1 - Radio set analyzers and how to use them, L. Van der Mel
      No. 2 - Modern vacuum tubes and how they work, Robert Hertzberg
      No. 3 - The superheterodyne book, Clyde Fitch
      No. 4 - Modern radio hook-ups: The best radio circuits, R.D. Washburne
      No. 6 - Bringing electric sets up to date and modernizing radio receivers, Clifford E. Denton
      No. 7 - Radio kinks and wrinkles for service men and experimenters, C.W. Palmer
      No. 8 - Radio questions and answers, R.D. Washburne
      No. 9 - Automobile radio and servicing, Louis Martin
      No. 11 - Point-to-point resistance measurements, Clifford E. Denton
      No. 12 - Public address installation and service, J.T. Bernsley
      No. 13 - ABC of air conditioning, Paul D. Harrigan
      No. 14 - Pocket radio guide, N.H. Lessem
      No. 16 - Practical radio circuits, David Bellare
      No. 18 - Point-to-point resistance analysis, Bertram M. Freed
      No. 19 - Practical radio kinks and short cuts, B. Baker Bryant
      No. 20 - The cathode-ray oscilloscope: Theory and practical applications, Charles Sicuranza
      No. 23 - Practical public address, B. Baker Bryant
      No. 24 - Automobile radio principles and practice, B. Baker Bryant
    - Radio-Craft Library, 1931-1941; no. 25-28; 4 volumes (Box 6)
      No. 25 - Home-made radio test instruments
      No. 26 - Modern battery radio sets [2 copies]
      No. 27 - Modern radio servicing technique
      No. 28 - All about frequency modulation
    - Radio-Craft Library, 1946-1947; no. 30, 35-37; no. 36 is captioned "Gernsback Library"; all titles are "prepared by the editors of Radio-Craft" (Box 6)
      No. 30 - Unusual patented circuits 1944-1946
      No. 35 - Amateur radio builder's guide [2 copies]
      No. 26 - Radio test instruments
      No. 37 - Elementary radio servicing
    - Radio-Electronics, 1973-1981; miscellaneous issues; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Radio-Electronics 50th Anniversary Issue, 1979; one as originally issues, one bound as commemorative volume; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Radio-Electronics tables of contents, 1958-1981; also includes front covers; 6 folders (Box 39)
    - Short wave beginner's book, 1933 (Box 6)
    - Short wave coil data book, 1937 (Box 6)
    - Short wave guide, 1936 (Box 6)
    - Short wave radio quiz book and kinks, 1938 (Box 6)
    - Telefiction annual, 1962; vol. A, no. 1 (Box 6)
    - TV: It's a cinch! E. Aisberg, 1957; front cover has "Gernsback Library No. 62" (Box 6)
    - Wireless blue book, 1909-1910 (Box 6)
    - Fragments, 1916; 1922; reproductions of scattered pages, instructions for "radiumscope," etc. (Box 6)
    - Uncertain, 1927 (Box 7)
      Two publications entitled "What radio set shall I buy?" and "The Radio Listener's Monthly Log Book." Publisher for both is The Consrad Co. Inc., but covers and interior are full of ads for other Gernsback publications so these are likely also his publications.
  - Miscellaneous
    - Artwork, circa 1945 (Oversize 1)